<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Ansvvere to the petitions of the traytours and rebelles in Lyncolneshyre</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1509-1547 : Henry VIII)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1536</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 9 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A02936</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13077.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103769</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99839514</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99839514</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3942</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A02936)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3942)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 59:08)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Ansvvere to the petitions of the traytours and rebelles in Lyncolneshyre</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1509-1547 : Henry VIII)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>In aedibus Thomae Bertheleti],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Londini :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno. M.D.XXXVI. [1536]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication and printer's name from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Formerly STC 15650.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 15650 on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴.</note>
                  <note>Leaves cropped at head with slight loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Lincolnshire, England --  History --  Sources --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:3942:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3942:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ANSVVERE TO THE PETITIONS OF THE <hi>Traytours and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belles in Lyncolneſhyre.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>ANNO. M.D.XXXVI.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:3942:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3942:2"/>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>IRST VVE BEGIN</hi> and make anſwere to the
.iiii. and .vi. articles, bycauſe vppon them de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendeth moche of the reſt. Concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge choſyng of counſailours, I neuer haue redde hard nor knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that princis counſaylours and prelates ſhulde be appoynted by rude and ignorant common people, nor that they were perſones mete or of habilitie to diſcerne and choſe mete and ſufficient cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſailours for a prince. Howe preſumptuous than are ye the rude co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mons of one ſhire, and that one of the moſt brute and beaſtely of the hole realme, and of leaſte experience, to fynde faulte with your prince for the electinge of his counſaylours and prelatis? and to take vpon you, contrary to goddis lawe &amp; mans lawe, to rule your prince, whome ye are bounde by all lawes to obey and ſerue with both your lyues landes and goodes, and for noo worldly cauſe to withſtand: the contrary wherof you like traytours and rebelles haue attempted, and not lyke trewe ſubiectes as ye name your ſelfes.</p>
            <p>¶ <hi>AS TO THE</hi> ſuppreſſion of religyous houſes ano monaſteries, we woll, that ye and all our ſubiectes ſhoulde welle knowe, that this is graunted vs by all the nobles ſpirituall and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall of this our realme, and by all the comons of the ſame, by act of parlyament, and not ſet forth by any counſaylour or counſaylours vppon theyr
<pb facs="tcp:3942:3"/> mere wyll and fantaſy, as ye ful falſely wolde per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade our realme to beleue. And where ye allege, that the ſeruice of god is moch therby diminiſhed, the trouth therof is contrary, for there be no hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes ſuppreſſed, where god was welle ſerued, but where moſte vice miſchiefe and abhomination of lyuynge was vſed: And that doth well appere by their owne confeſſions ſubſcribed with their owne handes, in the tyme of our vyſitations, and yet were ſuffred a great many of them (more than we neded by thacte) to ſtande: wherin if they amende not theyr liuynge, we feare, we haue more to aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere for, than for the ſuppeſſion of all the reſte. And as for the hoſpitalitie, for the reliefe of poore people, we wonder ye be not aſſhamed to affirme, that they haue ben a greatte relyefe to our people, whan a great many or the moſt part hath not paſt iiii. or .v. religious perſons in them, &amp; dyuers but one, whiche ſpente the ſubſtaunce of the goodes of their houſes in nouryſhynge of vice and abhomy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable lyuynge. Nowe what vnkyndenes and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturalitie may we impute to you and al our ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes (that be of that mynde) that had leauer ſuche an vnthrifty ſorte of vicious perſones ſhuld enioy ſuche poſſeſſions profites &amp; emolume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, as grow of the ſayde houſes, to the mayntenaunce of theyr vnthrifte lyfe, than we your naturall prince, ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raygne lorde, and kynge, whiche doothe and hath ſpente more in your defences of our owne, then .vi. tymes they be worth.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:3942:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>¶ <hi>AS TOVCHYNGE</hi> the acte or dies, we meruaile what madnes is in your braine, or vpon what grounde ye wolde take auctoritie vpon you to cauſe vs to breake thoſe lawes &amp; ſtatutes, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che by all the nobles knyghtes and gentylmen of this realme (whome the ſame chiefelye toucheth) hath ben graunted and aſſented to, ſeynge in noo maner of thynges it touchethe you the baſſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons of our realme. Alſo the groundes of thoſe vſes were falſe, and neuer admytted by any lawe: But vſurped vpon the prince, contrary to all equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and iuſtice, as it hath bene openly bothe diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and declared by all the well lerned men of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glande in weſtmynſter halle: whereby ye may welle perceyue, howe madde and vnreaſonable your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandes be, boothe in that and the reſte, and howe vnmete it is for vs and diſhonorable, to graunt or aſſente vnto, and leſſe mete and decente for you in ſuche rebellyous ſorte to demaunde the ſame of your prince.</p>
            <p>¶ <hi>AS TOVCHYNGE</hi> the .xv. whiche ye de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde of vs to be releaſed, Thynke ye that we be ſoo faynte harted, that perforce ye of one ſhyre, were ye a great many mo, coude compell vs with your inſurrections and ſuch rebellious demeanor, to remytte the ſame? or thynke ye that any man wil or maye take you to be trewe ſubiectes, that fyrſte make a ſhewe of a louynge graunt, and than par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force wold compel your ſouerayne lorde and kyng
<pb facs="tcp:3942:4"/> to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> payment wherof is not yet commen: ye and ſeinge the ſame wyll not counteruayle the tenth peny of the charges, which we do and dayely muſt ſuſteygne for your tuition and ſafegarde. Make you ſure, by your occaſions of this your ingratitudes vnnaturalnes and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyndeneſſe to vs nowe adminyſtred, ye gyue vs cauſe, whiche hath alwayes benne as moche dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate to your welthes as euer was king, not ſo mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che to ſette our ſtudye for the ſettynge forwarde of the ſame, ſeing howe vnkyndely and vntrewly ye deale now with vs without any cauſe or occaſion. And doubte ye not, thoughe ye haue no grace nor naturalnes in you to conſider your duitie of alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giaunce to your kynge and ſoueraygne lorde, the reſt of our realme we doubt not, hath. And we and they ſhal ſo loke on this cauſe, that we truſt it ſhal be to your confuſion, if accordynge to our former letters ye ſubmitte not your ſelfes.</p>
            <p>¶ <hi>AS TOVCHYNGE</hi> the fyrſte fruites, we lette you wyte, it is a thynge graunted vs by acte of parlyament alſo, for the ſupportation of parte of the great and exceſſiue charges, whiche we ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porte and beare for the mayntenance of your wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes and other our ſubiectes. And we haue kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen alſo that ye our commons haue moche com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>playned in tymes paſſed, that the moſt of the goo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des landes and poſſeſſions of the realme, were in the ſpirituall mennes handes: and yet berynge
<pb facs="tcp:3942:4"/> vs in hand, that ye be as louing ſubiectes to vs as may be: ye can not fynde in your hartes, that your prince and ſoueraygne lorde ſhuld haue any parte therof: and yet it is nothyng preiudicial vnto you our commons, but to rebelle and vnlawfully ryſe agaynſt your prince, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to your duetie of alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giaunce and goddes commandement. Wherfore ſyrs remembre your folies and trayterous demea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, and ſhame not your natiue countrey of En<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>glande, nor offende no more ſoo greuouſely your vndoubted kynge and naturall prince, whiche al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weys hath ſhewed him ſelfe mooſte louynge vnto you: and remembre your duetie of allegiance, and that ye are bounde to obeye vs your kynge, bothe by goodes commaundement and lawe of nature. Wherfore we charge you eftſones vpon the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayde bondes and peynes, that ye withdrawe your ſelfes to your own houſes euery man, and no more to aſſemble co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to our lawes and your allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances, &amp; to cauſe the prouokers of you to this miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe, to be delyuered to our lieutenantes handes or ours, &amp; you your ſelfes to ſubmitte you to ſuche condygne puniſhment, as we and our nobles ſhal thynke you worthy: For dout you not els that we and our nobles can nor wyll ſuffre this iniurie at your handes vnreuenged, if ye gyue not place to vs of ſouerayntie, and ſhew your ſelfes as bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>den and obedient ſubiectis, and no more to entremedle your ſelfes from henſforth with the weighty affai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res of the realme, the direction wherof only apper<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teyneth
<pb facs="tcp:3942:5"/> to vs your kyng, and ſuche noble men and counſaylours, as we lyſt to elect and chuſe to haue the orderynge of the ſame. And thus we pray vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to almyghty god, to gyue you grace to doo your duities, to vſe your ſelfes towarde vs lyke trewe and faythefull ſubiectes, ſo as we may haue cauſe to order you thereafter, and rather obedyentely to conſent amongeſt you, to delyuer into thandes of our lieutenant .C. perſons, to be ordered according to their demerites at our wyll and pleaſure, than by your obſtinacy and wylfulnes, to put your ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fes your lyues, wyues, chyldren, landes, goodes, and cattalles, beſydes the indignation of god, in thutter aduenture of totall diſtruction and vtter ruine by force and violence of the ſwerde.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>LONDINI IN AEDIBVS THOMAE BER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THELETI RECII IMPRES<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SORIS.</p>
            <p>CVM PRIVILEGIO.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:3942:5"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
